Guide to the Time Inc. Production Department Records 1947-1969 MS 3009-RG 36
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Production Department Records
1947-1969
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 36
4 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
The Production Department was responsible for overseeing the production of Time Inc. magazines. One aspect of this was overseeing the supply of paper products from the East Texas Pulp and Paper Company (Eastex).
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials include contracts and are located in box R29.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: Series I. Production Engineering General Manager William J. Carter Files on the East Texas Pulp and Paper Company; and Series II. Paper Usage and Print Orders.
Historical Note
The Production Department was responsible for overseeing the production of Time Inc. magazines and so was involved in purchasing needed supplies and arranging for printing.
The Production Department oversaw the supply of paper products from the East Texas Pulp and Paper Company (Eastex).
Provenance
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the files of Production Engineering General Manager William J. Carter regarding the Production Company's interactions with Time Inc. subsidiary the East Texas Pulp and Paper Company and reports on paper usage and print orders for Time Inc. magazines. Documents include correspondence, memoranda, reports, meeting minutes, statistical and financial information, and machinery schematics.
Corporation records; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Corporations -- History; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Organization files; Time, inc. -- Archives; Time, inc. -- History; Time, inc. -- Management
- Series I. Production Engineering General Manager William J. Carter Files on the East Texas Pulp and Paper Company, 1947-1958; 2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
  Biographical Note
  According to the Time Inc. department head lists, in 1955 William J. Carter was the Assistant Production Manager overseeing paper operations and planning. By 1960 he was promoted to Production Engineering General Manager overseeing Production Department Business Manager David House and Development and Technical Director Paul Thoma. The three of them were members of the Time Laboratory and Eastex Committee developing research programs for new products and production techniques.
  Citation:
  Time Inc. Reference Files, MS 3009-RG 3, New-York Historical Society
  Historical Note
  The East Texas Pulp and Paper Company, often referred to as "Eastex," was incorporated in December 1952 by Time Inc. and the Houston Oil Company. Located in Evadale, Texas, the company was organized by Richard A. McDonald, under the guidance of Charles Stillman, with R. M. "Mike" Buckley being made Executive Vice President and General Manager. The original purpose of the company was to provide paper supplies for Time Inc. magazines, however, the unit ended up producing mainly pulp and paperboard. In 1956 the Houston Oil Company was liquidated with Time Inc. acquiring Houston's interest in Eastex.
  Scope and Contents
  William J. Carter's files document the Production Department's interactions with Time Inc. subsidiary the East Texas Pulp and Paper Company (Eastex). His files contain extensive correspondence and other records forwarded from his employee Technical Director Paul Thoma.
  Records includes bleach board and other paper samples; agreements and contracts; correspondence; memoranda; reports; oversize printing machinery schematics; meeting minutes of East Texas and Springdale Committees on Research and Development, summaries and handwritten notes; spreadsheets with statistical and financial information; and a small number of photographs and maps.
  Correspondence, memoranda, and reports cover a number of subjects including machinery specifications; results of printing and coating tests; comparison of different paper stock and observations from other paper plants visited; projected expenses; updates on processes being tested and the work done thus far; negotiating with other companies in the paper field; discussions of different methods of paper bleaching; proposed agreements and contract discussions; market analysis for the products made by Eastex; recommendations and investigations on the expansion plans for Eastex; comparison and estimated costs of different procedures; plans for the establishment of the paper mill; and the research program developed by Time Laboratory in Springdale, Connecticut.
  Arrangement Note
  The series is organized alphabetically.
  - Agreements and Other Materials Related to the Sale of Houston Oil Company [Restricted], 1956 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Agreements and Other Materials Related to the Sale of Houston Oil Company [Restricted], 1956 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Beloit Paper Machine, 1952-1954 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 1)
  - Beloit Paper Machine [Restricted], 1952 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Bleached Board, 1953 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 2)
  - Board Coater (Springdale), 1954-1958 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 3-4)
  - Board Coater (Springdale) [Restricted], 1954 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Bonds Purchase Agreement: First and Second Closings [Restricted], 1954 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Booz, Allen & Hamilton, 1952 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 5)
  - Certificate of Necessity Application, 1951-1953 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 6)
  - Certificate of Necessity Application [Restricted], 1951-1953 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Champion Paper & Fibre Company, 1947-1948 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 7)
  - Champion Paper & Fibre Company [Restricted], 1947-1948 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Champion Paper & Fibre Company [Restricted], 1950-1956 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Chip and Pulpwood Agreement [Restricted], 1954 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Chlorine Dioxide Process, 1953-1954 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 8)
  - Coating Installations: Springdale Report on Alternative Coating Installations for Eastex (Exhibits), 1957 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 9)
  - Contract: Gas [Restricted], 1952 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Contract: Davis, William P. [Restricted], 1952 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Contract: Organization of the Pulp Company, 1952 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 10)
  - Economic Prospects, 1951-1952 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 11)
  - Expansion, 1956-1957 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 11)
  - Freight Rates, 1951-1952 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 13)
  - Hydraulic Barking vs. Drum Barking, 1953 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 14)
  - Loan Application [Restricted], 1952-1953 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Market Report: No. 2 Machine, 1956 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 15)
  - Market Survey, 1957 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 16)
  - Market Survey (Roos), 1952 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 17)
  - Memoranda: Miscelleneous Research, 1956-1958 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1951-1952 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous [Restricted], 1951-1952 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Miscellaneous, 1952 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous [Restricted], 1952 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Miscellaneous, 1951 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous [Resticted], 1951 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Miscellaneous, 1948-1950 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous [Restricted], 1948-1950 (Offsite-box R29)
  - National Council for Stream Improvement, 1947-1954 (Offsite-box 2249, Folder 23-25)
  - National Council for Stream Improvement [Restricted], 1953-1954 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Natwick Report, 1952-1953 (Offsite-box 2250, Folder 1)
  - Packaging Expansion, 1952-1953 (Offsite-box 2250, Folder 2)
  - Payout Schedules, 1951 (Offsite-box 2250, Folder 3)
  - Potlatch Industries, 1952 (Offsite-box 2250, Folder 4)
  - Presentation to Springdale, 1957 (Offsite-box 2250, Folder 5)
  - Resin Research, Inc., 1956-1957 (Offsite-box 2250, Folder 6)
  - Series B Notes Purchase Agreement: First Closing [Restricted], 1953 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Series C Notes Purchase Agreement: First Closing [Restricted], 1953 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Springdale Research Committee, 1955-1958 (Offsite-box 2250, Folder 7-8)
  - Stock Subscription Agreement: Second Closing [Restricted], 1953 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Stock Subscription Agreement: Third Closing [Restricted], 1953 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Stock Subscription Agreement: Fourth Closing [Restricted], 1953 (Offsite-box R29)
  - Wood Pulp, 1953-1956 (Offsite-box 2250, Folder 9)
- Series II. Paper Usage and Print Orders, 1965-1969; 2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
  Series II consists of reports on paper purchases and usage for Time Inc. magazines.
  Arrangement
  Series II is arranged alphabetically.
  - Pages and Print Orders: All Magazines 1967 (Offsite-box 4099, Folder 1)
  - Pages and Print Orders: All Magazines 1968 (Offsite-box 4099, Folder 2)
  - Pages and Print Orders: All Magazines 1969 (Offsite-box 4099, Folder 3-4)
  - Paper Orders 1st Quarter 1969 (Offsite-box 4099, Folder 5)
  - Paper Orders 2nd Quarter 1969 (Offsite-box 4099, Folder 6)
  - Paper Purchases 3rd and 4th Quarters 1969 (Offsite-box 4099, Folder 7)
  - Paper Usage 1st Half 1965 (Offsite-box 4099, Folder 8)
  - Paper Usage 2nd Half 1965 (Offsite-box 4099, Folder 9)
  - Paper Usage 1st Half 1966 (Offsite-box 4099, Folder 10)
  - Paper Usage 2nd Half 1966 (Offsite-box 4099, Folder 11)
  - Paper Usage 1967 (Offsite-box 4100, Folder 1)
  - Paper Usage 1st Half 1968 (Offsite-box 4100, Folder 2)
  - Paper Usage 2nd Half 1968 (Offsite-box 4100, Folder 3)
  - Paper Usage 1st Half 1969 (Offsite-box 4100, Folder 4)
  - Paper Usage 2nd Half 1969 (Offsite-box 4100, Folder 5)
  - St. Franciville Paper Company: #1 and #2 Paper Machines: Statistics 1969 (Offsite-box 4100, Folder 6)
  - St. Franciville Paper Company: Audit File: Working Papers and Reports 1969 (Offsite-box 4100, Folder 7)